[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a lot of interest in the distinctions in practice, you know, attainments, or identifying with certain attainments, and being able to call yourself a sotāpanna, an anāgāmī, an arahant, so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you call yourself a sotāpanna, for example,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you still suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, yeah, it's quite... it's quite normal that people would just sort of try to
[SPEAKER_01]: tailor and mold terms and terminologies to the basically what they would want them to mean and be.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just how the mind works.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the familiarity with the suttas is necessary, because if you read and see what the Buddha meant by sotāpanna, then you realize, okay, so these are the qualifications.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said it before, I think,
[SPEAKER_01]: When I first read... it was...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was Aya Khema.
[SPEAKER_01]: She had that paper on sotāpati and the three fetters that I found online.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was still a layman.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it was quite... well, saying that it was watered down, it's an understatement, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: She was saying that we are already sotāpānas, because we all know that rituals are empty.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, bowing to a shrine means nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: We all know that the Buddha was the greatest teacher, and we all know that modern science has proven that there is really no substance, like a substance of the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I remember thinking that I'm all great, so I'm a Sotāpanna then.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then immediately I thought, well, from the suffering point of view,
[SPEAKER_01]: And being free from suffering, free from liability to suffering, what difference does it make then?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize that type of sotāpanna makes no difference, which then means that's not sotāpatti, because the Buddha said what sotāpatti is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Four noble truths and freedom from suffering, seven grains of sand left, in comparison to the mountain of suffering destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you can call yourself whatever you want, but the reality is, do you... are you still liable to suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you still liable to not knowing escape from the areas of suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you still moved by the dukkha, afraid of dukkha?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the answer is yes, if the answer is I don't know, if the answer is maybe, means you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you're not a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you often keep insisting on that clear division.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either putujana or you're either sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you were saying also that from a putujana's point of view,
[SPEAKER_00]: The sotāpanna is like an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you, as a patujana, think you are practicing the dhamma, means you're implying that you know what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet the Buddha said, the knowledge of what dhamma is, begins with sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can't have it both ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you either don't know what dhamma is, means you're not a sotāpanna, or you know what dhamma is, means you're a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't say, I'm not a sotāpanna and I know what dhamma is, which is a reference point to the efforts in my practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how I know I'm progressing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that doesn't mean that whatever you do is wrong, but means that can only be known as right in hindsight after you get the right view, after you become a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the simile I told you before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine you're in
[SPEAKER_01]: All that matters is whether you're imprisoned or you're free, you escaped.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the efforts you do in prison towards the escape will be the efforts of escape only after you escaped.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you haven't escaped, even if you spend 20 years digging a tunnel, you're still prisoner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the point here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not that your efforts are useless, but unless you're a sotāpanna, they are useless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you haven't escaped.
[SPEAKER_01]: When your life comes to the end, it's not measured by, like, you know, what's waiting for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not measured by how hard you tried, or whether you tried or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's measured whether you escaped or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same when, you know, if the guards catch you or you die before you escaped the prison, no, all of your effort basically was useless, because you remain a prisoner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when we insist on this black and white division, when I insist on the black and white division is so that you will always maintain the context of the goal where it matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't matter if you thinned out the wall of the prison,
[SPEAKER_01]: This much, or this much.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is on which side of the wall you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you die, even if there is just one inch of wall left, well, you die the prisoner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, now you're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are on a limited time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not gonna live forever, and not your every next rebirth will head towards nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who knows?
[SPEAKER_01]: And more likely than not, it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the chance you have now, to be aware of the possibilities of escape, and the effort towards escape to make, is... it's a limited time.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, the guards might just bust in and catch you, and you're done, and they'll move you to another prison.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you trying or ignoring the fact that you're still a prisoner, so that you can kind of give more value to your efforts of escape, is a foolish thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have no reference of the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might have been digging the wall for 20 years, practicing the dhamma, but you don't know if there is another 200 meters of that wall.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know because you haven't escaped.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's wishful thinking to think that without having escaped the prison, your efforts are bringing you closer to the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only once you escape the prison, when you look back, you can see, yes, such and such effort brought me closer to the escape, and hence, I escaped.
[SPEAKER_01]: But until you escaped, you don't wanna... you should not be entertaining the notion of, I am closer to the escape, because you might not be, and you don't know whether you are or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly uttujana sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that everything Puthujana does is wrong, but until he becomes a sotāpanna, he should pretty much regard everything with a pinch of salt and as might be wrong or insufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's, again, you don't lose anything, by the way, except maybe a bit of your complacency.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you keep that in mind, that only escape matters, that's the ultimate goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's going to be more unpleasant to you to maintain that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because of that unpleasant context, you will have the direction to strive for, the measure to achieve.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you say, oh, well, that's, you know, tall order.
[SPEAKER_01]: All that matters is trying your best.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just what prisoner will tell himself, who is aware that he's still a prisoner and he cannot bear that reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then he just tries to mask it and make it more of that which it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... Oh, it doesn't matter the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: The escape matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it doesn't matter, you wouldn't have tried to escape in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: If becoming a sotāpanna doesn't matter, you wouldn't have even read the suttas and tried to practice it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the escape from suffering doesn't matter, you wouldn't have been doing this already.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be saying that it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know that it matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it's black and white.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very black and white.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's good for you to think that it's black and white.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you start making it grey,
[SPEAKER_00]: Complacency.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be a complacent prisoner, who likes to think that he's getting there with the escape, but in reality has no idea how much of that wall is left for him to dig, and whether he's going to get caught or not, and be sent to a dungeon, or something where he cannot dig through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, plenty of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's tied with that notion of basically forgetting that you are on a borrowed time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your practice now, unless has passed that threshold of sotāpati, as the Buddha would say, unless you pass the threshold of sotāpati, no amount of your practice then is guaranteed that will be picked up and taken again.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you might spend years in the realm that will be completely unsuitable for any practice of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the point of view of aeons, of actions performed in the realms that are completely against the dhamma, 20 years of your practice and meditation is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, keep that in mind, and don't lose perspective, and don't try and water down
[SPEAKER_01]: The threshold of success, which is sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why we say, basically, sotāpanna or higher is the only ones that should not be fearing rebirth and what's next.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because at most, they have a limited time before they fully free their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's again, it's a win-win.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing you lose is complacency here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're making effort great, and also think of this as a threshold even better.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're gonna make twice as much effort then.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you try to argue against this point, it's only because you want to compensate for the lack of effort, or basically try to pretend that you somehow know what the escape is, while simultaneously admitting that you haven't escaped.
[SPEAKER_00]: You hope the escape is safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too unpleasant to admit that you are a prisoner.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's kind of the necessary step, because that will then make you really want to escape.